all right look Sean here I don't want to
toot my own horn but beep beep this is
this is a this is an interview that
somebody else did with me uh David Pell
who you might know online as the writing
guy he uh invited me out to San
Francisco and we did an interview for
his podcast called how I write and my
episode is doing so well so well it is I
have this little Chrome extension this
thing is doing 11x 11x means it is 11
times higher performing than his normal
video
something good is in this video that
it's doing 11x on YouTube and it's all
about storytelling it's all about
writing uh it's stuff that a lot of
people ask me about but I'd never have
taken that time to sit down and talk
about it well David got me to sit down
and tell you everything that I know
about this stuff um I hope you like it I
was a little sick during the interview
but it was my Michael Jordan Flu Game I
came I came prepared and I brought the
heat um I'm really hyping this up and
it's because I'm excited about it I'm
really proud of this interview it's
doing really well a lot of people are
messaging about it so we want he asked
David hey can we run this on our feed um
you know we took the took the episode
from him we're going to run it on our
feed it's basically an interview where
he's the interviewer and I'm the guest
talking about storytelling and writing
so if you like those two things you're
going to like this episode all right
enjoy this episode with me and
[Music]
Dav story is a 5-second moment of change
whoa what do that mean you want to work
backwards from the em the only things
people will share is things that are LOL
WTF OMG all here now the broadcast so
like what should I do next time I sit
down to write the real great writers I
believe are great at framing their ideas
oh interesting so Mr Beast Steve
Bartlett Dave Chappelle Huss minhaj
those are the people I try to learn from
you know I could teach a 30second master
class it's just
this Shan Pur is one of those guys that
I really wanted to learn from I've spent
a lot of time thinking about how to tell
better stories by listening to good
storytellers but Sean has really
deconstructed the storytelling process
and you hear people saying all the time
oh storytelling is really important you
should get really good at it but there's
not a lot of people who come in with
concrete clear Frameworks like he does
so this is a masterclass on storytelling
come on in it's time to roll I said this
to you when we first show cans but this
podcast was probably the biggest
increase in terms of how much I've
admired a guest and how much that's
grown through the prep process and so I
just want to compliment you on that and
in particular there's a lot of things
that you do really well in your writing
that I'm not good at
and this is one of those episodes where
I just have a bunch of questions and I'm
here to make my writing way better and
the place I want to start is
storytelling I have no Frameworks for
think about storytelling before you do
storytelling can I give you a compliment
on your compliment yeah so great
compliment first of all very specific uh
but the second is actually it's a
writing tip which is I didn't the thing
you said where you're like you know I
started kind of going down your rabbit
hole and my like whatever respect for
your whatever you said like my uh
whatever your score went up a lot during
that process uh I learned this from
these two guys Dylan and Henry they're
young guys they were like 21 when I met
him and they were recording these videos
I was like how many views do these get
and they were like oh nobody watches
these and I'm like but you guys are like
really trying like is it like someday
somebody will watch these he's like yeah
specifically we're creating a binge bank
and I was like what's a binge bank and
he goes it's when you basically stack
material so that like even though each
one of these if we just looked at the
view counts it'd be kind of discouraging
like H not that many people read this or
watched this um but they were like we
started to think about it differently
instead we said all right each one's not
getting that many views but I'm creating
a bank where if somebody ever said I'm
curious about this guy I want to learn
more what is this guy all about
that in the next hour you would walk out
with like my reputation would be way
higher with you right like you would
feel like you know me you would like me
you would respect me and it changed the
way I thought about that and so then I
because I used to not I used to like be
like very um result driven it's like ah
if it's not immediately paying off it's
hard for me to get excited about it but
when I thought of the binge bank I just
thought oh I need to create this library
that if anybody like if David is going
to do research he's going to spend an
hour or two hours going like down the
rabbit hole I need to leave a little
breadcrumb trail that by the end he's
like I love this guy I'm all about this
guy guess where I ended up guess what
like the final thing was which was like
the shebang of all right I totally old
blog post that I probably forgot about
as my guest it's like that 40 page PDF
with all your main principles that was
like the pool I swam in for the longest
and I ended up there yeah who knows but
like that's the you leave that trail you
could proba I should probably do it
better but like this idea of create a
binge bank I think is so much more
valuable than a resume or
portfolio it's like people will come
knocking they will get curious about you
and like give them away to uh to just
binge your content like it's a Netflix
show and by after two hours they should
feel like you're the man that's that's a
goal I think people should have so what
do you do to do that intentionally well
the first thing is like you don't get
discouraged by like how small your thing
is today that was like the first part
which is if you create something and the
feedback loop is not quite there you're
either going to just willower your way
to keep going you're going to be a very
wise person and say results take time
I'm neither of those things bad at
willpower and not that wise right like I
I kind of know that's the answer but
it's so it's a way to trick yourself and
um the way to trick yourself is to say
oh yeah this one thing it doesn't have
to like go viral for this to be
successful this is for my binge bank I
know the idea of a [__] b is important
I want to have that as an asset that's
there for me so what are the 10 things
that somebody should go cons asse and I
started paying attention to that and and
started putting that together one of the
things that you are very good at is that
I feel like you're just good at learning
skills putting names to them and this is
a good time to dive into the
storytelling so I guess that you had
this whole day you're like oh I'm going
to go check out Aaron Torin and he
always comes back to like this one core
principle tell me about what you've
learned from storytelling and then maybe
even like the meta of how you learned
new skills the story tell thing is cool
cuz you know I think everybody
intuitively know storytelling is a
pretty dope ability and I look for this
mismatch between things that have a lot
of value but you're not taught or even
better it sounds kind of lame to say
you're working on it like if I find that
I'm like oh this is a good one uh
another example of that to me is uh
enthusiasm anybody who's been around
somebody who's like got high energy
enthusiasm you like that person that's
inherently like a it's a very likable
trait of course there's over-the-top
obnoxious version but it generally you
want to air on the side of have energy
have enthusiasm those are people you
want to do projects with work with be
involved with but nobody will ever be
like yeah I'm practicing my enthusiasm
right like I'm practicing this um that
sentence doesn't even compute so if
there's a thing that has value that
other people don't practice or try at uh
and even better it's like almost taboo
or lame to say you do it I've found that
those skills are actually like premium
skills to me cuz you almost like
differentiate yourself in the
marketplace store storytelling is
another one of those joke telling is
another one of those like if you're like
um I am working on like getting funnier
they're like are you trying to be a
comedian no like you like funny people
though right like of course everybody
does whether it's relationships work
content creation whatever you're doing
if you're humor level if you're more
humorous people will like it better
nobody practices so it's like what do
you expect just you know to magically
happen like we kind of know everything
comes pra everything is Downstream of
practice so storytelling is one of those
skills where I knew that I loved it
whenever I met somebody who's a great
Storyteller I wanted to get better at it
so then who's the best in the world of
this right that's the next question one
of the people that came to mind when I
Googled around was Ain sorin and uh he's
written you know famous TV shows I even
West Wing news room The Social Network
movie it's great for writing dialogue
and in these interviews he says this
thing he's like they're like What's the
key storytelling like can you teach a
like a three-hour Master Class he's like
I could teach a 30 second master class
like like it's just this
it's intention and obstacle and he said
it even better he goes I worship at the
altar of intention and obstacle and I
was like I don't even know what the hell
he's talking about but the way this
guy's serious about it tells me like I
need to go dig in what is he talking
about so what does this mean intention
and obstacle is just at any given moment
the the hero of the story whether it's
you or someone you're talking about has
to have a very clear intention what do
they want and under that is like why do
they want it how bad do they want it
what happens if they don't get it right
that's like goes into intention and then
obstacle like who's in the way right so
you know Harry Potter wants to live
what's in his way Voldemort trying to
kill him the most powerful wizard of all
time is trying to kill him right
intention and obstacle and basically if
you watch if you read any story or you
watch any movie you should be able to
pause at any moment and just point at
the screen and just say what's what do
they want right now and what's in their
way and if you ever go like five minutes
without that being clear people will
lose their attention will Drift Away and
so um once I realized that I made that
the central premise of any story and
what I realized was that this was a
incredibly powerful tool it is the
fundamental like building block of
Storytelling and um the more interesting
thing which we could talk about is it
doesn't have to be life or death all
right everyone really quick if you've
heard this podcast before you know that
Sean and I think that the most important
skill set you need in business is
copywriting and so what we did was we
went through
all of the podcasts that we've done it's
like 500 of them and we found all the
best copyrighting tips our resources our
Frameworks our templates we aggregated
all of them into one simple document so
you can skim it all and get everything
that we've ever talked about with
copyrighting it's in the link below it's
awesome check it out so most people
think of it when like the example I even
gave was Harry Potter trying to live and
E most evil War are trying to kill him
okay cool but you can shrink that down
and actually you get bonus points when
you can do intention obstacle on a lower
Stakes moment so I wanted a croissant
and all the places were closed but I
need my croissant you need your
croissant and the but the audience has
to believe that you truly needed it and
you got to tell them be like you got to
make them believe that you really wanted
it ideally because you actually did
right you know you don't have to
fabricate the story it should be real
I'll give you an example I was at a um
like executive offsite uh my company I
just got acquired I got put on the exact
team of this now like 2000 person
company and I don't I feel a little bit
out of place like I've never worked in a
company bigger than too many people and
I wanted to use storytelling to kind of
like as a crutch as that's one of my
tools in my toolkit how could I use this
to better myself all right so um we're
supposed to go around the circle and
like say what's been going on uh or like
what's something what's this what's
something recently that happened that
you want to share with the group some BS
like uh Icebreaker and every single
person just did it in a work context oh
we're working on this thing but then
this person on my team has did this
problem or quit or whatever oh we're
working on this thing but then legal
said this it's kind of like boring
boring
boring and uh I was like yeah recently
uh had a big moment big day and uh okay
pause right get people curious I said um
I just moved out of the house I was
young right so I was like I just moved
out of the house I'm living in my own
place I've been living there for a year
now but I've never invited my mom over
and my mom's in badging why don't you
invite me over what she doesn't know is
I'd never invite her over because I
don't want to I don't know how to host
she was always the host if someone came
over I don't know how to do adult things
so people are kind of laughing right cuz
I'm but I'm like I was like I had been
trying to get her to like treat me like
an adult but the reality was I'm like
I'm not I'm actually still a little
little boy right and so I'm telling the
story about how my mom comes over and I
decide to cook I decide to cook brussels
sprouts the most Adult food there is
problem is don't know how to cook
brussels sprouts something I'm doing it
blah blah blah and I tell the story of
cooking the Brussels sprouts and I just
kid you not everybody's like everybody's
entertained they listen to it during the
break everybody made a point to come up
and be like dude that bruss story was
hilarious um that was so that was so
funny like what was that and what even
just happened they kind of couldn't even
explain it and for me it was just
another example of using storytelling
even on low stakes moments actually
builds likability and um fandom more so
than the dramatic I was skiing and there
was an avalanche that's cool but it's
unrelatable and actually there's
something fundamentally unlikable about
it and I want write uh usually if I want
to write something it's because I'm
trying to whatever I'm trying to have
fun but I'm also trying to build an
audience of people who like me or are
fans of me or get customers who want to
you know buy my product or whatever I
try to use likeability for that it was
interesting I was at a sort of a very
fancy dinner like multi-billionaires
house and it was one of those dinners
where everyone is like you know people
had flown in for the dinner and there's
like an Olympian who's sitting across
the table who was was like a big fan of
growing up and and we're all going
around doing introductions and it's my
time to do the
introduction so I'm nervous I really
want to impress everybody like one of my
childhood Heroes
00 2 o' right and uh I you know sort of
pp myself up and I talk about hey this
is what I do for a living and I'm like I
crushed it you know man everyone love
this and we're we're hanging out after
after dinner I'm back in my apartment My
Buddy goes yo you did the worst job ever
like that was a horrible intro it's like
what are you talking about every word to
the Bone like have my on liners like
ready to go crushed it he's like no you
were just trying to sound impressive in
a moment like that you tell a funny
story or you make a joke and you lighten
the mood you did exactly the wrong thing
right yeah that's uh first of all great
friend to say that great friend can we
call that out and you're you're
absolutely right uh I learned this from
hust minage the comedian cuz I was going
to go on stage I was like hey dude like
you do this for a living I don't know do
this stuff and he goes you want to um he
goes comedy is a low status gang so he
goes you know you're going to be up on
stage and you're nervous so your natural
tendency is going to be to Puff your
chest out to kind of project this false
bravado but he's like um actually what
you want to do is build connection with
people and you build connection with
people through um vulnerability through
uh low low stakes uh through um low
status specifically he starts his comedy
special I went and wrote it out to try
to like understand what he does his last
comedy special he starts out he's
sitting on a stool he's talking about
how intention him and his wife been
trying to get pregnant um and they
haven't been able to and they went to a
doctor and he's like the worst news ever
it was my fault my balls don't work
basically right like is there a lower
status thing as a guy than to be like I
you know my junk doesn't doesn't perform
also just the way like that that word
choice is inherently funny exactly and
so you know he's obviously a master at
this and trying to trying to learn from
people who are like I'm in business I
don't try to learn how to be a better
Storyteller or better writer from
business people why would I do that I
would try to learn from the people who
their thing is storytelling or writing
or entertainment because they're going
to be the best at this you know Aon
sorin comedians those are the people I
try to learn from and so uh I think that
was one principle that sounds like you
you learned the lesson the hard way too
how is storytelling different for you in
writing versus speaking it's not that
different um in general one of my
biggest writing rules is write like you
talk um most people have this false uh
thing we do I think it's from school
like School kind of teaches you like
they're like read Shakespeare write
these essays you know I need six pages
uh six pages minimum you know double
spaced you know all this stuff use a big
vocabulary all the things that don't
work in the real world you learn in
school I think what school teaches you
is basically just pretend like uh Hey be
something you're totally not that's what
good writing is in the real world I
don't think that's true I think you know
good writing is simple good writing is
easy to read good writing is
entertaining to read good writing has a
voice um it's not just like this you
know archaic sounding thing um so
anyways I you know one of the principles
is write like you talk so if I'm going
to write a story I will actually say it
first and then I'll just write down what
I said that's like a starting point for
me because for most people myself
included if you sit down the like blank
page you know of death is like the most
intimidating thing it's very hard to
even get started but if you are stuck
and you just say okay so what is the
story like forget the words what are you
trying to say I'm trying to tell the
story about the one time with the spouts
and blah blah blah um cool what makes it
interesting all right great um where did
it start what's the start of the story
well start is when I blah blah blah and
what's the end well the end was when
this happened all right cool sounds like
you got a beginning middle end you know
what happened and you roughly hit the
outline cool maybe now start writing and
so uh WR like you talk is an important
principle and the other thing is there
are nuances that are different so for
example in writing I'll use a ton of
like parentheses because you can't do
that in uh you kind of you can break the
fourth wall basically when when you
write but when you talk it would be like
me saying um so we were going this way
you know we we always take that route
right it's like a that's a parenthesis
is when you're talking when you're
writing it's actually much easier to do
um but when you're talking you can use
pauses and a dramatic pause how do you
do a dramatic pause in writing it's kind
of hard to do you have to like use like
line breaks or do da D DT whatever right
like you got to try that so you some
tools are a little bit different but I
would say 80 to 90% of it is the same to
me have you learned anything about the
pacing of a story like the how you drag
it out or compress it like does that
change for different platforms how do
you think about that definitely um you
know I think another misconception
is shorter the better like you know too
long is too boring and actually um you
know anything could be any length it
just say you can only be as long as it
is interesting listen general rule it
can only be as long as it is interesting
if you can go this long you know a long
you know blog post but it's interesting
the whole way fantastic that's the right
length however you should always try to
understand like what is your level of
credibility or Buy in with the audience
so here in a podcast you can kind of
Riff in a podcast you can be like dude
what we could talk about something we
said in the lobby or be like oh you just
had Sam Alman on does he have a
bodyguard like we could just not talk
about writing for five minutes totally
fine however if it's cold traffic on the
internet you better have like an amazing
headline and a first line that's going
to hook people and be right about the
match what the headline was because you
don't you don't have that reputation
with them so if you know your audience's
level of buyin with you you can kind of
um dance around subjects versus be very
direct and immediate and trying to
provide value right away um to hook
people right away so you know Tik Tok is
a platform where you're
swiping like and if it's not interesting
in the first like9 seconds you're gone
so on Tik Tok you see people right away
try to say a thing on podcast you'll see
people shoot the [__] um and build you
know there's a chemistry thing because
people aren't going to swipe away from
the podcast in in the first 30 seconds
it's not usually how people consume
podcasts and so you got to know your
medium and you got to know your audience
what's the level of buying you have how
do you think about the hooks for a story
like one of the things I've noticed with
Comedians and really studied is how fast
they're able to build context they can
do it in like six to eight words where
some people just go on and on and on and
on and on it drones and that hook of how
you bring people into the story is super
important I agree um however I so what
is a hook so a hook is basic it's the
first thing you're going to say trying
to hook their attention great I think
actually right now for for the type of
person who's going to listen to this you
probably have studied a little bit of
copyrighting maybe or you kind of pay
attention to what like oh this person's
blowing up on Twitter what do they do oh
there would like you know they write
their threads and the first line of
their thread is like here's the
unbelievable story about how this you
know Chinese immigrant took a simple
thimble and turned it into $10 billion
whatever some like unbelievable sounding
of that you're like oh you have to pick
it's like maximum clickbait right I
actually think that hooks somewhat
overrated underrated is frames so what's
a frame so a frame is you take an
idea and an idea can be this big or it
could be this big depending on the frame
so I can be like um you know uh what's I
don't have a good example top my head
but we'll do one that we just talked
about that hust the comedy thing right I
told a little story about what he's
doing in um in his line so I could just
say here's what he did at the start of
his thing I could say here's what you
can learn about public speaking from one
of the greatest public speakers in the
world H Min right so I could take the
same content where I'm going to talk
about starting with a low status thing
but I can put it in the frame of this is
not just for comedians this is actually
when you're at a dinner party and you're
supposed to make an intro and you don't
know what the hell to say um this is how
to not make an ass out of yourself you
Chang the frame right and so I think
that more important than a hook which is
just like a grab you by the throat
aention Grabber is think about how
you're going to frame your ideas hooks
are about the words you're going to
write frames are about the idea and how
you're going to make that idea relevant
and how you're going to connect two
ideas that seem unrelated to be related
the real great writers I believe are
great at framing their ideas more so
than like just coming up with that
perfect oneline hook thing that's GNA
like you know just kind of trick the
person into clicking yeah let's get
super concrete here so you wrote a super
viral thread on clubhouse and this was
the standard way to do a frame so it
says one parentheses Clubhouse
existential threat number one time
devalue ratio Le let's brainstorm and
you're like jargon fancy words like that
wasn't me wri that was somebody else
exactly yeah I don't like it it like it
brainstorm like no storyline and then it
didn't do that well and you come in
you're like so dot dot dot everyone
seems to think Clubhouse is the next big
thing but I think it's going to fail
here's how I think it all goes down yes
why did you choose that so that if you
compare the two and like on your YouTube
you should put these like side by side
so people could see it the other one was
written by this guy Chris who created an
app that was kind of like Clubhouse went
super viral was called secret back in
the day I don't know if you remember
this it's called secer it's super viral
they raised like hundred million the
founder like sold some secondary bought
a Ferrari like it was like the hit
product for like a very short am of time
and then it died so if anyone has The
credibility to say why Clubhouse might
fail that guy was actually the guy the
problem was he was extremely dry told no
story and just said and use like very
like you know 12th grade reading level
jargon like Clubhouse is existential
threat the the time to Value ratio like
immediately felt like homework whereas
my thing was everybody thinks X but I
think Y and more the most important part
was here's how I think it's going to go
down not here's why I'm right so here's
how it's going to go down is basically
like gossip it's story um here's why is
logic and rationale so that's kind of
why I wrote it that way was and then the
rest of the thread the reason this
thread got like 20 million people to
read it was
because I I wrote it almost like a
screenplay I was like I didn't say
here's the five problems with Clubhouse
I wrote you're the founder of Clubhouse
first of all [__] yeah you know you're
winning everybody is talking about your
app your app is cool you know Kanye's in
your DMs VCS are throwing money at you
and I set it up right like you that's
the setup that's you right now and
already you know if you're reading that
this is not how most business Tech
Twitter writing goes most business Tech
Twitter writing goes is it it's an
intelligence contest and I was telling a
story and um and so you know that's why
I think it worked I think if I had
written it with the you know me trying
to be the the 9,000 IQ guy in the room
it would not have worked so when you see
people say that I'm writing now and I'm
like all right I'm not going to do
intelligence contest I'm going to try to
do exactly what Aon sorin said there's
intention and there's obstacle I'm going
to frame what I'm saying in terms of
story I'm going to focus on the frame
and say that my writing still is just
like yo this is lame what do you think
is going on there that
makes it feel dry or like it lacks a
sense of momentum well in the same way
that comedy is great but not every line
should be a joke uh storytelling is
great and not every piece of content
needs a story um so I think one
challenge is like I wrote that one as a
story it did great that doesn't mean
everything I write online is like this
screenplay story type of thing that
worked in that situation it's not going
to work in every situation so you got to
know like the tools and when to use them
Hammer is not good if you're just trying
to open a door sometimes a key is what
you need and so that's the first thing
don't just force it in the second thing
is like you probably need reps like I
don't know I've done this a lot of times
that wasn't the first story I've ever
written so if you're like cool I'm going
to get better at storytelling be
prepared like tell a 100 stories
starting with maximum cringe and get to
nut cringe right like but it's going to
take a 100 expect that it's going to
take a 100 stabs at this and
specifically in 100 intelligent reps so
it's like do it and then the next one
you have to be like what could I do
better oh my Hook was a little weak
there or oh you know it droned on too
long or I don't really have a point
maybe this shouldn't have been a story
maybe it should have been something else
and so 100 reps where each one you try
to say what's one thing I can do better
than the last time just one thing that's
it and then you just keep going and if
you could do a 100 of those then I bet
your stories will work it's not going to
be it's not going to feel forced because
you'll learn the skill through those 100
reps this is the Mr Beast ISM of uh he's
like everybody asked me like how do you
do YouTube good he I tell them all the
same exact thing make 100 videos and
every video make one make do something
better better than you did before any
anything doesn't even matter what it is
one thing better than before do 100 then
come back and talk to me and he's like
two things happen first of all Nobody
Does it they all wanted just like some
answer they had no no intention of
actually going and doing the work and
then of the few people who actually do
the work they never need to talk to me
again by the 100th one they figured it
out they're doing great you know like
they never come back for advice that's
why it's the perfect advice to give
someone cuz it's true and it saves both
of us the hassle uh you know if you
actually followed it yeah what did you
learn from story
Worthy storyworthy is a amazing book by
this like teacher guy who's like this 20
time storytelling champion of the moth
storytelling I didn't I didn't even know
what this thing was but whatever if
you're the champion of something I paid
a little bit of attention he's got this
book and in the book it's basically how
to tell better
stories I would say you know probably
worth reading the book he's got one
thing that I really took which was
Stakes so he's like um every great story
needs Stakes meaning if the story is
intention and obstacle but if you don't
make it clear what's at stake for the
for the person if they don't get it um
then the story is not going to have very
not be very compelling so you know when
you tell a story let's say it's the and
it doesn't have to be high stakes like
it doesn't he's actually very again the
other thing he says is like don't tell
like it calls it like vacation RS so
it's like don't just tell a story but
there great night you had the party cuz
like nobody cares nobody wants to hear
about your vacation nobody wants to hear
about your cool College party you went
to like just fundamentally those are bad
Stories the second thing is like a great
story is not just I was swimming in the
ocean and a shark bit me and I survived
like it doesn't need to be extreme and
again it's actually almost better if
it's not um but you still need Stakes so
how do you have Stakes even if it's not
a shark biting you off and his his
answer was um the stakes come from the
emotion so as long as you believe that
that other person was going to feel a
certain way then the story has Stakes so
for example if I'm trying to impress my
mom doing the brussel sprouts
embarrassment is what's on the line
right like I'm going to be embarrassed
and my ego is going to take a hit so as
long as you believe that that's true for
me the story will be entertaining um
when it's prop when I actually tell it
when it's actually delivered um the
other one he says is he goes what is a
story story is a 5-second moment of
change whoa what is happening a 5 Second
so he's like you know uh everything that
you tell in the story comes to this one
moment this 5 Seconds where the
character is transformed you know just I
use movies cuz it's easier that most
people don't have like a big Archive of
writing in their head but like we've all
watched the same shows and movies every
romcom is like some version of the
following uh the guy's a player and he's
never going to settle down that's the
start of the movie or she's a high
powerered lawyer who's doing great in
her career but never made enough time
for love that's always the start of the
story there's only two romcom right like
she was in love they thought she thought
they would get happily married he broke
her heart start of the romcom so well
guess what the ending of the romcom is
going to be always the exact opposite of
that if she was the high powerered
lawyer who never made time for love
she's now going to be in love and she's
going to actually quit her job as a
lawyer and be like open up a bakery
right like that's how the movie is going
to end or if he didn't want to settle
down and he was a player by the end he's
going to be chasing her and he's going
to like propose to her right he's going
to want to settle down so spoiler for
all romcoms ever and um it's actually
all movies ever die hard Jurassic Park
you could do the same exercise watch the
opening one minute the end is going to
be that
character the opposite of his current
lifestyle or belief system or habits um
you know Scrooge hates Christmas he
loves Christmas or whatever it's all
every movie every story is the same so
the heart of the story is the 5-second
moment when they actually made the
transformation when they switched and
it's usually when they lost it all when
they had the Heartbreak when they hit
rock bottom when they had no choice but
to be brave because they were finally
cornered like whatever it is right uh
you know in Batman when it's like he's
in the cave and he's got to get out and
nobody's ever made it out I don't know
if you remember this part of the Dark
Knight or or one of one of the Batman
movies and uh the mentor was like only
one person's ever got out he's like how
did he do it um he's like he didn't use
the rope they like May basically he
jumped with no safety net and so the
5-second moment of change is the
character climbs up the thing takes off
the Rope if he doesn't make this jump
he's going to die but actually because
he was going because of that makes the
leap and actually makes it that's the
transformation moment everything is
based all stories if you don't know
what's the 5sec moment of change for the
for the main character you don't really
have a great story how does this apply
or not apply to like the story of a
company like if I'm trying to tell the
story of for a passage or you know you
think of all these companies oh we
started in a garage we have no money
this what we believe right you have
Airbnb you have like the Obama O's and
then you have Brian chesky who's like
going to the houses and he's like taking
photos with his own camera he's like and
the hustle it's like these Founders
really believed so how does how do we
take these ideas and apply it to what
we're building the origin story of all
silly valy companies is is similar so
let's take Airbnb for example what was
the you know moment of change uh the
moment of change the origin story of
Airbnb is we were um broke jokes who had
right the beginning of the romcom we
were broke jokes not only did we not
have a successful company we didn't even
have an idea so like we were the worst
situation for an entrepreneur no money
no team no idea no respect no reputation
no nothing right even worse wrong
founding DNA we were all designers and
the narrative was you got to be an
engineer to build a you got to be a
developer to build a a te tech company
and so um well the moment of change was
basically they I think they had no money
um like they didn't have enough money to
pay rent or something like that so the
the moment of change was basically one
of them had a crazy idea to be like hey
what if we rent out our space here for
this there's a design conference in town
what if it create a like a bed and
breakfast for people who are coming
because all the hotels are sold out bed
and breakfast we don't have a we don't
have a hotel and they're like well we
could just put an air mattress here and
they laughed and they were like whatever
and then three people came stayed paid
the money and had a great time and
they're like holy [__] this might be a
thing and then there's several holy [__]
moments right there's like we ran out of
money again so we did the Obama O's
serial thing we uh they tell the story
about when they were getting knocked off
by a big um by the Samir Brothers of
Rocket internet they were cloning their
company and going to kill them and he
tells that story it's like we you know
fa this life or death death moment and
then we had to make a decision and we
changed we went from being scared to
being like all right we're going to
compete with these guys we're going to
beat them um and that's the moment
that's that's what the each of those
micro stories is about the way I've
learned this is you have uh it's called
Signature stories so your signature
stories are the like the four or five
stories that if I only could tell you
these four or five you would know
everything there is to know really about
me so for example your Origins story
like for you with write of Passage
what's the origin story like I'm
assuming you didn't just create this cuz
life was good you already were good at
everything and uh and you know there
must have been some moment where you
were like I got to do something here
will you help me improve my origin yeah
give me what it is right now all right
so I worked this job at this New York
advertising agency and I was super
intimidated by my boss he's like 6'4 you
know big beard he's just not like super
welcoming guy super talented super
talented and I wasn't doing super well
my job and he sort of calls me into his
office and I was working on a pitch deck
for cardi I was trying to be all
impressive and stuff like that and I
wrote in the pitch deck that the idea
that we have
was going to be epic and he was like yo
that is not a good word to be using
you're not he said something to the
effect of you're not in college anymore
we don't write like that here and then
through writing that sentence he then
started saying hey you really need to
improve your writing you're just not a
good writer and I was like well you know
I tried learning to write in school I
don't even like writing my whole job is
writing and I got to get good at this so
that was in like November then we go
through December I get a raise I'm like
oh my goodness this going to be great
life's going well then January 5th 7
months out of college I get laid
off and of course in my head I'm like I
got laid off cuz I'm not a good writer
uhoh I got to learn this craft but I
don't even like writing but then I'm
seeing all these people who are good at
writing and they're just making moves on
the internet and stuff so I spend years
two three years and I'm learning how to
ride I start building an audience and
during that time people reach out to me
they're like hey you're pretty good at
this can you start teaching me how to do
it and I'm like wait I learned all these
things on my own I had to figure these
things out out of desperation for how to
learn how to write then that led into
write a passage and that's how the
company got started okay great so let's
Workshop that cool all right so um let's
go back to the origin let's do so
there's a beginning middle and end
beginning you're start of your romcom
you're working in a job you're not you
said you're not doing so well your boss
kind of embarrassed is you uh and you
end up getting laid off act one of of
the movie uh I think to make that part
just to make that part better so I think
you have the element there act three is
I you know so we know act one is going
to be don't like my job and my job
doesn't like me even worse my job
doesn't like me right uh second part is
I'm not doing so well and I'm kind of
embarrassed and I'm kind of intimidated
by my boss great super relatable super
likable all that um you have a moment
where you got specifically embarrassed
around the epic thing calling you like a
college kid or whatever you're like okay
hopelessness um max pay got laid off
cool and I'm sure you had some feelings
about that act three is now I get paid
millions of dollars to teach people
writing and I'm doing a podcast
interviewing my writing Heroes and
they're like dude you're awesome I'm a
big fan okay great so we have the
element of an amazing Story how do we
actually make it better yeah so the
first part is your act one you didn't
focus on the pain enough the atttention
and the obstacle and the feelings you
had at that time so for example you said
I wasn't doing tooo good at the time and
then you're like but then I got promoted
or raise so I don't know what that is
right uh you know you might as well
leave the promotion raise out doesn't
really add to the story it's sort of
confusing conflicting messages right
never let the truth get in the way of a
great story let's start with that so why
did you not think you were doing
well the company was constantly trying
to figure out what do we do with this
person I I I can't believe this happened
but he literally brought me into his
office and he goes I need you to stop
thinking like Jeff Bezos and I was like
can you explain he's like do your job
you are a sales guy focus on that I
don't want you focus on the the future
of media and where that's going and so
there's just a lot of tension there and
he and I never really got along that
well right so yeah I think you want to F
I bet you if you zoomed in go back to
the memory bank and you remember like
any moments where you felt the opposite
of how you're going to feel at the end
at the end you feel really proud and
you've accomplished and you've overcome
but at the beginning you probably felt
embarrassed you know uh somewhat uh
insecure uh whatever so for example if
you were like I um yeah I remember there
was this new guy that just got hired and
I was training I was like trying to like
welcome him and train him a little bit
and then he got promoted before I did I
was like I'm doing something wrong or
you know at my performance review I
remember there's a category for pros and
he had like three words and then cons or
whatever like needs needs Improvement
was huge right a little anecdote like
that I think will like make that more
real of uh what was the moments where
you said where if you said I wasn't
doing so well that it really hit home
for you um you know something like that
let me just wrap everything we've spoken
about into what I'm gathering is it's
the romcom I got my beginning I got my
end I want a perfect yin-yang between
them okay then what I want is I want to
build up to those 5 Seconds of change so
I want one emotion lead up to that
change that is the moment of of of
tension where something pivots then I
get to the end there is the opposite and
then what I want to do is intention and
outcome obstacle intention and obstacle
thank you so my intention is I want to
be good I want to be good at my job I
want to be valued I want to be respected
actually I could even bring it into like
I want to be a worthy human being and
I'm in my first job and I'm like dude
you have no skills so I have that and
I'm like my job is about being a writer
and my boss thinks that I'm not very
good so now of my obstacle so that's
sort of what I'm getting from you right
yes exactly you you nailed it um now
let's go to the 5-second cuz what you
said was basically some version of
you're like the beginning was pretty
good and the ending was pretty good uh
the middle you were like so then I got
laid off and so then I started thinking
about well I want to improve my writing
sounds like an arbitrary Epiphany maybe
there was a mentor that told you
something or maybe you read something
online that inspired you or maybe you
had a long talk with yourself on a long
walk one night and you were like you
know what screw this right probably a
moment when you decided actually I'm
going to get good at this that's usually
a very important part of every story was
like what triggered the turnaround um so
you want to know that and then you want
to explain that part um and then you
basically were like and then I got
better and then everything was great
it's like whoa what you fast forwarded
the Montage too fast like what triggered
the turnaround and then what did you
actually go do um not like in a long
specific but like what's the first thing
you started to do to get momentum and
then what was like maybe some resistance
you felt that you overcame because like
you know the Pixar rules for
storytelling I if you seen this 22 Yeah
the most important one I don't know what
the 22s say but I remember one which was
um something like the hero doesn't have
to win um the audience loves the hero
because of the way they try and that was
really important to me I was like oh
that's right every Underdog Story is
lovable because of how hard they try and
if somebody just try something and
immediately it works that's not a very
good story and you're not very like you
don't feel good for them
so you got to say what you tried what
resistance you felt and then how you
overcame that resistance it doesn't have
to be a long thing but you want to make
it feel real uh and the last thing I'm
I'm kind of emphasizing to you that I
think anybody can do in their
storytelling is um you're not saying
what happened you're zooming into
moments to explain how you felt with
ideally some relatable visual or audio
like moment so it's like I remember he
said this to me and I'll never forget
these three words he said you know like
whatever some some sentence or I
remember looking
around and you know there was nobody
else there like to Tony Robbins I'm a
big Tony Robbins fan he does an amazing
job telling his story and he's like I
remember sitting in my apartment I
looked in the bathroom and I was doing I
had because I used to do dishes in the
bathtub because my my dishwasher didn't
work so I'd soap up the bathtub and he's
all he's trying to say is I'm a loser I
was a loser now I'm super successful why
because I'm Tony Robins and I figured it
out and you can too but but first he has
to convince you that he used to be a
loser otherwise the whole Tony Robins
stick doesn't work so he's like how do I
convince somebody I'm a loser I could
say that I wasn't doing too well or I
could say that I used to have to wash my
dishes in a bathtub because that paints
a picture of a loser he's like I
remember I was s then he says I was s in
my apartment and I didn't have any
furniture because I didn't have any
money so I just had this one chair like
I didn't have a sofa I had a hard chair
that I used to sit on he's like it was
just a chair he's like and I remember uh
the a song was playing that was like
there's some song where he's like I
don't have a friend or something like
that it's only me in my chair and he's
like dude that's me it's just me in the
stupid chair and he's like so I went for
a run he's like even though I hadn't run
in years I was overweight I went for a
run and even when my lungs were burning
I was like no you you may be a loser at
all things in life but you're not going
to lose this run and he tells the story
and it's kind of inspiring when you're
hearing this and he's just zoomed into
one moment that's visual that's audio
that's a feeling and he's convinced you
of that before state so that the after
has some impact the two things that I'm
getting there there is first you can
tell a story a story is not a record of
what happened absolutely it is not you
saying this happened this happened this
happened this happened it is almost this
it's a transformation it's a oh
interesting the story is just a change
the world was one way and then it was
another way I was one way and then I was
another way my company was failing and
then it was succeeding all the story is
is just change you only want to include
the what happened so much as it explains
how that change came to be um yeah it's
not as just a timeline of events and
then you're also really queuing into
emotion
yeah how H that's what like people
respond to you know um like in my
writing course I used to teach um I used
to teach this one thing that I was like
you know you want to work backwards from
the from the emotion I learned this from
uh a guy who used to be my my I don't
know intern or something like that I we
hired him when he was 20 years old Steve
Bartley
today a lot of people know St Bartlett
he's got a big podcast called di CEO
he's built a company he's done a bunch
of he's on Dragons Den like he's a
famous guy now I met Steve when I was 20
or when he was 20 I was 25 maybe and uh
he flew from the UK he lived in our
office like slept in our office and he
wanted to work with us and we worked
together for I don't know what nine
months or a year or something like that
um and Steve was awesome in a bunch of
ways he was obviously just like a
21-year-old in a bunch of other ways but
the aw awesome thing I remember was he
was like he told me something he goes I
just think about what is Jenny in her
bedroom going to think when she sees
this like who's Jenny who's Jenny what
what are you talking about he's like oh
like if we're making a piece of content
that's going to go on social media
social media is Jenny in her bed laying
down just scrolling just swiping and
she's like basically this has to make
Jenny and Jenny like stop think
something and share this with their
friends otherwise it's going nowhere
there was no point in writing this thing
or doing this thing cuz it created no
reaction from the person they're just
going to keep swiping the world is full
of infinite content we only stop at
things that we have some reaction to and
um so I stored that away and then I
heard the same idea from another person
this is how you know a good good idea
the BuzzFeed guy goes everything we do
at BuzzFeed is about Debbie at her desk
I'm like Jenny in her bedroom Debbie at
her desk it's going on here see he goes
he goes the most powerful Network in the
world is the board at work Network he
goes all my BuzzFeed was like growing
like crazy at the time he's like
BuzzFeed basically Taps into if
someone's bored at work and they just
want to like you know have a distraction
for five minutes we want to make a piece
of content that will distract them and
get them to forward it to a bunch of
other people who are also bored at work
right and that's the whole network is
the board atwork Network all right
second time I heard the idea then I
heard the idea third time this gu Chris
Quigley he ran a advertising agency that
would make videos go viral and at the
time I was like going viral is like a
lottery ticket like how do you do a
viral video I don't know it's just like
something amazing must happen so I go
what's your hit rate on virality like
one out of 100 two out of 100 he goes no
like eight out of 10 I go eight out of
10 and he's like yeah look he showed me
their their views I was like how do you
do this he's like well you know over
time the more viral videos you make you
have like a base of an audience but he's
like that just gets you like some people
will see it but how viral it goes is how
much they share it he goes so what we do
is we work backwards from an emotion he
goes the only things people will share
is things that are L WTF OMG aww like
all the acronyms for all the emotions so
like oh my god wow like ha right like if
it doesn't do that nobody will share it
so he goes we first start with this is
the desired reaction we have then we'll
write a script or write a write a a blog
post or whatever and then we'll go check
do we think that's going to create this
reaction to somebody no all right let's
Juice It Up how do we make it more funny
how do we make it more outraging how do
we make it more endearing and
heartwarming like whatever those are and
uh so once I heard that three times I
was like okay I get it I need to create
a reac reaction out of the average
person just in their bedroom at their
desk and I need to start with the
emotion my target emotion and then work
backwards from that write the thing that
will create that emotion yeah it's funny
because when you write you're like okay
I'm publishing this on the internet
bunch of people are going to read it you
know get a big audience and so you think
of hey there's all these people but
actually you're just writing to Debbie
in her bedroom or Sally at her desk you
know and people consume your content
alone and when you're writing you are
writing to one person in one place at
one moment in time and you have to
remember that because the nature of the
connection that you're trying to make is
different and to double down on that
idea in a lot of our media environment
especially with a platform like Twitter
when you scroll Twitter like you're on
the throne you're on the bus you're
waiting in line you're you know your
friends 7 minutes late you're like come
on where the heck are you you I'm trying
to reservations coming up and you're
just sort of browsing browsing browsing
and your brain's only like halfway on
and if you can really first understand
your own State when you're in that
environment and then write to the person
who's in that state now you have a very
keen sense of who is this person and
you're writing for one person even
though if you're looking you're seeing
hey 119,000 Impressions those are not
119,000 people at once like a football
game they're 119,000 in individual
people at 119,000 individual instances
in time and if you think like that you
communicate very differently yes
perfectly said you're writing to one
person at One Moment In Time that's I
think a very good point and the other uh
thing that this reminded me of is do you
know this person Miss Excel have you
seen this PR yeah yeah so she um for
anyone who doesn't know she's basically
like an Excel influencer for lack of a
better word um she basically teaches
people Excel trick tricks but the reason
she got popular she went on Tik Tok she
started dancing while like putting an
Excel trick on the screen or a tip on
the screen um weird combo but it works I
was reading some interview with her and
they were like how do you create your
content like what's what's your process
and I was like I'm curious what her
process is and she goes uh I don't she's
like it's kind of weird she's like um
most people if you say what's the
process and they're like consistency
like wake up at a certain time start
right away you got to write every day
you got to post at a certain time you
got do all these things she's like I
don't do any of that she goes I
literally first
like just Chang my own energy she's like
I work she's like I'm kind of wo wo W
that way but like I basically get myself
into a peak State of Mind like I get
myself into a certain mood and a c
certain State of Mind where I feel
magnetic I feel charismatic I feel
energetic I feel she's like it's like an
like a it's literally like a science
called energetics she's like I work on
my energy and two things happen one
ideas start coming to me much faster
than if I sat down and said what are
some ideas I need to post some content
today and so she's like I just work with
something I say I let ideas come to me
an idea will hit and as soon as it hits
she's like I run to my phone hit record
and I just do it she because I believe
all content is just energy transferred
through the phone it's my energy
shifting to you my emotion that I'm how
I feel about this if I feel excited
about this Insight that I have or
excited about this this tip that I have
I want to get you excited about that tip
too and the best way to do that is for
me to be there first and I think this is
a very underrated thing for writers
because most writers they're not
performers all performers know this no
athlete goes on the field without being
warmed up and being hyped up no stage
performer goes on stage just kind of
cold and low energy but almost every
writer starts cold and low energy and
just sits there somewhat miserably and
um and there's even some weird Glory
from like this like I don't know this
like pain that martyr ship of like how
you need to be as a writer I think
that's all stupid um I think it's very
similar to performing any way I think
you should get yourself into a great
state of mind and then have that energy
and then sit down and write and let it
flow and let that energy rip through you
so that the the other person who reads
it is going to feel the same excitement
you have about the Insight or feel the
same excitement you have about this plan
or whatever it is um you know you want
that to come with it and a lot of times
when people write they have this idea
they're away from the computer like
they're at the bar with their friends
they're on a walk with somebody else
they're Thanksgiving dinner they're like
man you know auntie auntie Diana she has
no idea what's going on that woman was
crazy and you're so annoyed at like
11:00 p.m. at Thanksgiving and then you
try to write like 3 days later and the
problem is they're not capturing the
energy that Miss Excel is capturing
before she does the videos and people
end up writing in such a sober state
that their writing ends up being boring
and sterile 100% the thing I said at the
beginning of this podcast where was like
I look for things that I think are
important that other people don't
practice Overlook or be too embarrassed
to say they're working on this is an
exact example of them of one of those
nobody wants to work on their like State
their energy they don't want you know
Miss Excel does she's like I'm going to
make myself magnetic before I make
content well I like that that's pretty
cool I don't I don't know what that
means if that sounds provocative right
like okay that's better than whatever
the hell I'm feeling uh when I sit down
to write okay that's a new standard for
me I'm going to do that and so um I
think most people would probably in
their heart believe that this is true
that if you kind of got your energy
right before you did the thing it
probably turn out better nobody's going
to do it which is the best part it's the
Arbitrage it's how a less talented
person like me can do really well wait
all do here it's now the broadcast so
like what so what should I do next time
I sit down to write how does this
actually work when I get to dance do
some jumping jacks like what do I
actually exactly that's exactly right so
State change is three things number one
radical change in your physiology so you
can Sprint you can do push-ups You Can
Dance you can um do 20 air squats you
can dump your face in cold water
whatever it is you will it's the fastest
way to change how you feel is a radical
change in your physiology it's the first
thing um so do that that's that's the
very first thing um I have a friend
who's a professional poker player he
does the same thing he goes during poker
players are like notoriously degenerates
like you're literally sitting there in a
casino which is like the worst air
pumped in environment there's no windows
and you're around other degenerates all
day people are smoking it's bad um he's
like a monk and he during a tournament
in the breaks he goes in the parking lot
and he does win Sprints he's not doing
it to be a better Runner he's not doing
it to increase his V2 Max he's doing it
because he wants to make a better
decision when he gets back to the table
he knows he makes better decisions when
he changes a state and um that's part of
his Edge why he's been a European like
you know poker champion and uh tour
Champion you know several years so first
thing is a change in your your um your
state the second thing is a change in
your focus so what are you even focused
on um where like you the way I imagine
is I have this laser beam of focus I
don't know if this is true but what I've
convinced myself which is if I just turn
my attention to this I will crush this
this will be amazing if I if I put 100%
of my focus on this podcast right now oh
this podcast didn't stand a chance and
the only limit to me is is where I'm
pointing the beam and if I'm trying to
point it in five different places or
whatever that's going to be a problem
this also works with like if you have to
write something and there's a deadline
if your focus is on the deadline it's
the wrong place to focus right if your
focus is on you know um your uh how hard
it is for you to do something if you're
focus on how hard it is it's not a good
place to focus like you need to focus on
the thing you want um so you know don't
focus on the wall where you're like
trying not to crash like turn right B
focus on where you're turning and then
the last one is basically your story so
what's the story you tell yourself um we
all have some story that we tell
ourselves and if you improve the story
you will change the state of mind that
you have so if I go into the sto if I go
into this podcast right now in my story
is um I'm just I'm doing a f to David
I'm just doing this oh man like you know
I had to drive an hour to come here and
you know this means I'm not going to be
able to do this thing and whatever
that's the wrong story obviously I'm not
going to perform very well I'm not going
to be in a peak State whereas if my
story was there was going to be someone
who listens to this one person one
person who's listening to this
podcast and they're going to hear one
thing that I say one story and they're
going to be like
wow I can't unhear that that was amazing
and that person was going to go on do
amazing things and they're going to
write me a letter one they and be like
dude that podcast you did changed my
life I'm going to approach this podcast
differently right I the different words
will come out of my mouth if my story
about what's happening is different so
similarly if you want to basically
change your state physiology first Focus
Second Story third nice one of the
moments I had around story that I
thought was really revealing was I I
work with a coach and we were talking
about my writing and I was in a slump I
was down and what's a writing slump what
does that mean I just wasn't vibing I
wasn't feeling it and I just wasn't
proud of the stuff that I was doing
and I couldn't get
inspired and
uh he said what is it that you want and
I said well you know I I used to write
these these pieces these long form
pieces that I was really proud of you
know what I want I want to be a creative
Force I want to be a creative Force
that's what I'm going for and I sit down
to write I'm like I want to be a
creative Force that's what I'm all about
and he's like hold on hold on hold on
stop stop the
train you said you used to be a good
writer and you would get in a great flow
what did you do back then that you don't
do now I was like
huh actually pretty simple I find an
idea that was interesting
I would try to figure out that idea for
myself and then I'd figure out for
myself and I'd say well then I got to
share this with other people and i' just
do that over and over and over again and
I never stopped that's all I did and
that's all I focused on he's like hold
on what you're saying is now you're
focused on being a creative Force that's
your story that's not working for you
let's get back to finding an interesting
idea not judging the interestingness
figuring it out for yourself and then
sharing it with others ever since that
no more slop right all that was was a
change in my story yes amazing uh that's
amazing and I think you know the other
part of what you said there which is
letting curiosity be the the guide the
driver um sounds very simple but all
great ideas are actually quite simple
it's the beauty of them you know there's
a I think there's a profound um benefit
of revisiting simple ideas and then
saying am I doing those um I don't look
for for new ideas as much as I look for
ideas I've already heard that I haven't
fully actualized yet and you know that's
one um you've read like Paul gram WR
this essay um great work I assuming
you've read that one yeah I recently I
read it two nights ago so good for the
first time he wrote it like a year ago
and it was like 13,000 words so I was
like I'm not doing that like it's too
long well when the student is ready the
teacher appears so I'm ready to I'm
thinking about what what do I want to
work on right now how do I want to do
this and I went back to that and in that
he he has this great line he goes if I
had to boil down all great work into one
one word it would be curiosity and he
says another thing which is curiosity
drives in a level of excitement he goes
and excitement excitement is really a
great indicator he goes excitement is
the engine and the rudder of the boat
it's the engine and that excitement is
motivating it's it's a driver to get you
to go do things but it's also the rudder
it also can point you in the right
direction if you don't know which path
to choose just choose the one that's
most exciting just go keep following
that
and that will lead you to the right
place it's excitement is the engine and
the rudder um I think is a really
powerful idea and every time I've
drifted away from that like you did like
I start with that good things happen and
then I'm like o now ambition is the
driver or um doing something that sounds
cool or important or money is the driver
and then like all the bad things happen
and I'm like [__] uh why aren't these
working and it's like well because you
stopped doing the working formula which
was leading to all these great things um
because you thought you need needed to
like you know you thought you need to do
something different and so many people
are like oh I hate writing and most of
the time it's that they associate
writing with doing things that they
don't want to do and then when they
think about well it's time to write they
subconsciously don't allow them to write
about the thing that they're the most
curious about or excited to write about
because in school that's not what you
get to do yeah no one's excited about
the average school paper maybe one or
two things but people just aren't
trained to think like that one of the
things
that I need to reconcile with you and
try to sort of figure out because got
two Sean ideas and we need to figure out
how they sort of come together
is this line that you have if you're in
your head you're dead love that line so
good at the same time you are always
deconstructing things you have you find
something that you like and you're like
hold on what's going on here let me try
to break it down okay I'm actually going
to go check out this book go talk to
this expert try to figure out what's
going on so how is it that you are
deconstructing thinking being fairly
analytical but at the same time not
getting in your head those things feel
like Polar Opposites to me yeah two
things one I read something yesterday uh
this like mini book online that was
called I think it's called like a
technique
for a technique for coming up with new
ideas it's like some old book um and in
it it said this thing he goes the uh the
most
valuable traits you can have sound like
opposites when you know if you pair them
together so he goes you know uh imagine
an entrepreneur who is both Visionary
and detail
oriented that's a that's a Steve Jobs
for example like Steve Jobs is famous
for being a Visionary he he doesn't ask
the consumer what they want they just
want Faster Horses he you know they want
a car actually right that's how he
invents you know the iPhone and figures
out what to do but he's insanely detail
oriented where he's like what is the
inside of the box look like and they're
like dude Steve nobody's going to look
at this he's like I'm going to look at
this I will know what's inside the box
it needs to be beautiful at that level
of detail pixel level detail um same
thing for all things right uh I consider
myself a creative person I'm also highly
analytical with data sounds like
opposites um and so there are many
things where the exact opposite if
paired together creates a like 1 plus 1
equals 3 type of reaction and um they're
often presented as false choices you're
either this type of person or you're
this type of person screw that be the
type person you want which sometimes
means having both gears and knowing when
to go into which gear when do I need to
be uh creative when do I need to be
analytical when do I need to be hard
charging entrepreneur when do I need to
be silly playful dad you know paint my
nails whatever right like I have to have
these gears to have the life I want
similarly you want to be in your head at
the times it makes sense to be in your
head the brain is a valuable tool it
just cannot be the master so the you you
know I need to be in my head when it's
about maybe it's uh analysis maybe it's
oh I'm feeling fear I need to actually
use logic and ask to myself is this fear
even true and what's the probability of
that and if that happened how would I
handle it I guess I would just do this I
guess it's not so scary after all so
usually um if the problem is emotion you
can solve it with emotion if the problem
is logic you can solve it with logic and
so I try to use them at the right times
the if you're in your head you're dead
is basically a has more of a life
philosophy than it is a work philosophy
which is people who kind of go around
life not feeling a whole lot and not
being present in the moment they're in
their head about stuff uh they're
missing life um and that's that's a
problem you know more so than than a
writing tactic have you ever seen that
advice from Ray Bradbury where he says
don't think you ever seen this so I
heard that what you said here and it
immediately reminded me he says I have a
sign and my typewriter it says don't
sink and I'm like okay that's
interesting he's like I'm trying to
surprise myself at the keyboard and the
only way to surprise myself is once I'm
in my head I can't do that and I think
that a lot of writing a first draft is
like this you're you're trying to get
outside of that part of your brain that
judges that condemns that says no no no
it's not good enough and just put stuff
onto the page and you know that you're
doing it well when what you're doing is
like whoa where did that come from where
did that come from where did that come
from and then the question is how do you
engineer yourself to do that like for me
if I'm sitting and typing can't do it
like my ideas that for me is where I do
editing the thing that was gamechanging
for me was voice transcription getting
really good because now I can stand and
talk talk and walk go outside walk and
talk just blab blah blah blah blab half
of Austin definitely thinks I'm some
sort of like crazy psychopath kind of
guy but you know what it's made my
writing better and a bunch of people I
work with they're like how do you just
bang out first draft so fast I'm like
cuz I don't sit and type like everybody
else does I just go for a walk
yeah I think that's a that's a great
point I think you need to to figure out
a way to engineer that for yourself so
you can consistently have it um I think
everybody's got a different version of
of how to do it what you said reminded
me of something though you go um you're
talking about ra BR don't think uh I
think this is a a very useful
troubleshooting tool so when you're
stuck there's many ways to get unstuck
and one way to get unstuck like I said
radical change in something physical you
do I me that's a good tactic music is a
good way to get unstuck too um but in
general a philosophy for how to get
unstuck is you're if you're stuck in the
specifics go General meaning if you're
stuck in the logistics of the how
something is going to happen it's not
quite adding up what you got to do is
not just keep trying to do this you can
just zoom right out go super General all
right super general what am I trying to
do here I'm trying to do this super
General um if I had all the superpowers
in the world well how would I do this
right super General is just like um
you know uh who's somebody who's done
this before or super General okay I
don't know exactly what type of thing I
want to write what inspires me right the
way to get out of these sometimes is to
go General to go uh and so even if like
don't think it's hard because very hard
to turn off the brain but it's not so
hard to redirect the brain and so
redirecting it I think is is a useful
tool you can redirect it towards I'm
going to go rock climb I'm go exercise
that'll take my brain off of it it can
also be I'm stuck in the muck here and I
need to just zoom out and that's it or
if I'm stuck in the general so for
example sometimes I'm stuck in the
general of like what do I want to be in
life and like you know what what do I
want to do and who am I and all this
stuff um specific what's the like what's
the best idea you heard in the last two
days what like if you were going to
write about that what would it be or
like what's the most interesting phone
call i' I've had um you know then you go
specific because you're stuck in the
general so it's a very useful thing to
do is just like to get unstuck know if
you're stuck in the specifics go General
if you're stuck in the general go
specific and you you'll redirect the
brain I want to switch over to talk
about voice you're really good
at putting your voice onto the page and
you do something very specific that I'm
not sure how consciously you do this but
you're so good at getting inside the
head of a reader to understand all right
how are they feeling about this in the
moment and basically you said earlier
breaking the fourth wall and then by
doing that building trust and connection
and then it creates this friendly
casualness as if we're having a
conversation that
my goodness that is levels away from
most from what most writers are able to
do have you ever read the Boron letters
years ago okay so this is uh mustre yeah
uh copyrighting copyrighting I'm
surprised you don't have them like
printed out of your pocket they're that
good so the Boron letters are this
amazing thing by this uh like kind of
renowned
copywriter Gary Halpert I think uh
writing to his
son and he's in jail so the writer is
now in jail he's writing to his son uh
Bond I think um is his name and so it's
like a series of 23 letters and um I put
they're hard to find too it's really
annoying they're hard there's like one
blog I put it I hosted them on my blog
now um because I was like this is crazy
that so valuable and so hard to find so
anyways um he posted he wrote these
letters and he just wrote it again to
one person he's like I'm Runing to my
son but obviously these were kind of
like general principles of life and
copyrighting and marketing and he's
teaching he's trying to teach him
everything he knows uh but the but
because of the way he wrote it with such
a casual like like warm relationship
like he's not even just writing to one
person he's writing to his son and
because he's writing to his son he's
like and this dear bond is where things
get interesting where he's like you're
probably wondering dad why do you say
this we're going to get to that but
first a little detour and he just
started writing so differently that I
was like oo I like this style this is
just like has a swag to it that uh that
is just like appealing to me
um so I started stealing that basically
I was like oh I'm going to write like
that I'm going to write like I'm writing
to one person and that one person is
like my little young grasshopper it's
like this is my kid or it's my my little
cousin or it's me when I was younger
it's like uh I know what you're thinking
blah blah blah but Mama Mia you're wrong
right and I'll just like try to like try
to just make it fun and interesting as
if it's written to one one one person
that has like a warm relationship
somebody that's kind of like I want to
be the Sensei and they that's how I
write in in where it's like a master
teacher relationship and other times
it's the opposite it's um I'm the
beginner and I know that other people
are more more knowledgeable about this
and I'll be like and I just will be open
about that I'll be like so being the
idiot that I am I'm going to I decided I
was going to do these three things I
knew there's probably a better way to do
this you probably know four four better
ways yourself you're probably staring at
this right now wondering how could this
guy be so dumb well the answer is blah
blah blah right and I'll I'll try to say
it like that cuz I'm just trying to make
it where I'm trying to imagine what is
the reader thinking at this what would I
think if I was them and then I try to
address that in the moment because it's
very frustrating to me
when like imagine if you ask somebody
this question you're like how did you do
it and they're like I just did this and
you're listen to a podcast and then that
podcast host doesn't ask them like wait
wait wait what do you mean it just
worked like how or what do you mean he
gave you a million dollars why did he
give you a million dollars right like
it's the most frustrating experience in
the world when that doesn't get
addressed so in writing I try to do that
too like I try to just call out the
thing I would be wondering about or I
would be skeptical of or I would be
excited about in that moment I just try
to include it in the the dialogue one of
the things that we talk about all the
time in read a passage one of my core
principles is imitate then innovate and
it's exactly what you did there so I
asked you a question and you said okay
have you ever heard of this thing well
Gary Halbert does this very well and
then what you did was you deconstructed
exactly how he does it and then you said
you found a general principle of his
work so you said he's not just writing
for one person he's writing to his son
and then the implications of that are
this this this and this and
the road map that you took to give me
that answer I think is very revealing of
how you think about writing where you
start somewhere you deconstruct and then
you say how does that show up in my own
world and then you try to build up a
generalizable principle that then you
can use for your toolkit whenever you're
typing yourself yes that's exactly right
uh I think that is a great thing for
anybody to try to do if you want to get
better at something that's a that's the
way yeah by the way I randomly just
thought of the best example of framing
from way
earlier while you were talking which is
kind of how the brain works the brain
relaxes and then something comes to it
um have you seen the Dave Chappelle
thing called Unforgiven have you seen
this on YouTube no all right so do you
remember a while back uh Dave Chappelle
was in a feud with um I think it was
Netflix
and he was like um the Chappelle show
was put on Netflix and he wasn't getting
any royalties so like it's his name it's
his face it's all his life's work and
not only was he not getting paid for it
he had had a big falling out with the
creators of the Chappelle show where
like he ended up quitting right when
they they the story what the time was
they offered him $50 million he said no
and he went to Africa and became a
crackhead instead that was like the
rumor like Dave shelle's a crackhead now
and he's in Africa and it was like and
he later he was like no I just said no
why did I have to be a crackhead in
Africa I went home like what are you
talking about so anyways here's the
objective his objective was he wanted
people to boycott the show how do you
get people to boycott the show you gotta
if you want to drive people to take
action you got to be smart with how
you're going to uh like how are you
going to persuade them through the
written word or in his case he wrote it
first and then he performed it on
stage and what he did was instead of
talking about Netflix or talking about
his show or saying go boycot my show
please he started
in a he reframed the problem in a
totally different way that I thought was
brilliant he just changed the frame
completely so he tells the story he goes
um I remember I was 14 years old first
time I did ever did comedy I was 14
years old I go to this comedy club and I
tell this joke and he's like I'm he's
I'm admit it I was good right away
comedy came naturally to me I'm not one
of those people who's like it took me a
decade he's like honestly I was good and
I was 14 15 or 15 years old I think and
he's like I was underage but but I was
good and he's like I came backstage and
there's a guy who's been doing this for
20 years and they were like Hey kid you
did pretty good man that that was good
and he's like one guy came to was like
hey man I like that joke I have this big
audition coming up for this TV show or
something like for this other thing you
mind if I use that joke and he's like
even as a kid I'm 15 this guy's you know
bigger older I looked up to this guy
he's like I um I didn't want to do it
cuz I was like my joke's all I got I got
no money all I have is a comedian is my
jokes he's like but you know this guy
was kind of asking I felt uncomfortable
he said he just needed it for this
audition so I was like all right man
like sure you can use the joke for the
audition guy's like all right cool he's
like several months later I go to the
club I'm about to perform that guy's
before me he tells my joke and the joke
kills he's like I was pissed and he's
like I didn't know what to do he's like
afterwards I went up to the guy again
I'm a 15-year-old kid I'm like he
basically is framing it as I'm this
powerless kid and this guy's taking
advantage of me and he goes
I told him I was like hey man you said
you were just going to use it for that
thing like I I don't want that I want my
joke back and um I think maybe he had
give him 100 bucks or something like
that and uh and the guy's like the guy
kind of roughed him up he grabbed him
and he was like I was just asking to be
nice you know I could just take it and
he's like I was scared I didn't know
what to do I let that guy take my joke
okay so that's he's I'm gon tell you
another story he tells a story about
later on he's in New York and he's uh
he's like I got a date with this
Jamaican girl he's like fine girl yeah
banging I couldn't wait to go on this
date but I didn't have any money I'm I'm
still a struggling comedian but now I'm
older I'm 22 24 or something like that
he's like and I walk around New York and
I see these guys doing like that three
card money where they like you know that
game and I'm watching it and guy puts
down 100 bucks moves the thing around I
know it's over here he guesses the wrong
one he loses he shows it's over there
next guy goes same thing puts down 20
bucks uh I know it's over there he picks
over here he loses I'm like God I could
do this so I step up I put all 100 bucks
down he like I'm going to double this
that I'll take them take my girl out
tonight I know the ball's over here I
say that one Ball's over there he's like
what the hell just happened he's like I
was pissed I lost 100 bucks I have this
date tonight it's like so I stuck around
and I watched and I realized those
tourists they didn't leave they were
still here and they did it again he's
like oh they hustled me like those guys
are in on it together they pretended not
to know it was and I was the mark who
came up and said oh I figured this out
they got me and then somebody else uh
came up and they were about to make the
same mistake and I told him don't do it
they're all in on
it and the guy goes oh okay and he
leaves he's like the guy RS him up again
and he goes hey man uh he goes I don't
care what you think he's like never get
between a man and his next meal he's
like you just took money out of my
pocket this is my job this is my
livelihood and taking away a man's
livelihood is the equivalent of killing
him he tells him that okay cool then he
finally gets to the Netflix story and he
basically weaves together the parts from
before he's like they didn't ask me if
they could put it on Netflix they didn't
ask me to basically like they didn't ask
for anything they just took my name took
my face took all my content they just
took it he's like and then the second
thing was that the people would say well
you signed the contract Dave he's like I
was a 21-year-old kid I hired lawyers to
read these contracts uh they told me
think I said this hey you can use this
forever in perpetuity in all parts of
the universe and they're like it's
standard Dave don't worry about it this
is standard Hollywood stuff don't don't
worry about it so he's like so I signed
it later on I realized those guys all go
out to dinner every week the lawyers on
my side their side they're all in on it
this is just like the three card money
that's how Hollywood is I was the mark
so yeah I signed it but whatever and he
got the whole audience on his side by
like making this argument by using these
two stories I think it is the most
brilliant like example of of PR or like
a written story that I have ever seen
the way by the end of that thing you're
like I will delete Netflix if they don't
take the show off and it's exactly what
happened people saw that that video on
YouTube it went super viral because it
was so well done um people boycot in
Netflix they took it off uh and they
Netflix said we don't have to do this
day but we voluntarily will do this like
we were also moved by your story uh
we're not going to put putell up there
unless you say we can do it even though
contractually we have the rights to do
whatever we want we're going to honor
the non-contract here I thought that was
the power of like you know reframing not
like oh I'm getting screwed I want money
to like a more Universal you know you're
getting picked on by the man you're
getting screwed by people who are all in
on it and I thought that was absolutely
brilliant that's yes you should go watch
this thing it's amazing yeah I want to
talk about
distribution so one of the things that
we're working on at R A Passage is what
I want to figure out is I want to figure
out how to take anybody people who don't
write all the time don't really have an
audience they've just published
something really good like say that you
are an absolute expert in like the
distribution of San Pino Waters from
like the little town in Italy how they
where they package it you know what's
the story of the label all that sort of
stuff and you are like this is how the
sparkling water boom came and I'm going
to tell the story of how it begins in a
little town in Italy with San pelo water
okay you have this expert he she never
written online they write something it's
awesome and I want to help them
distribute it they come to me they say
what do I do how should I talk them
through
that I think distribution is built over
time I don't think that's something you
can do from day one right like uh it's
kind of back to that 100 videos thing uh
from earlier if you're going to write
online there is sort of a um Beach head
moment you have to create you have to
create a trusted audience over time and
you have to know that the distribution
is earned why distribution is so
valuable because it's hard to replicate
so for example my buddy Jason used to
say this thing he goes oh I have the one
two three rule of interestingness what
does that mean he goes tell me one one
thing that's interesting right you tell
me one thing that's interesting about
San pelo I'll say that's interesting
tell me two things that's interesting
I'll be like those were interesting
that's two interesting things you tell
me three interesting things I'll say
you're interesting and this is just like
a general philosophy I think you should
have with writing is like you don't
deserve that like trusted follow or
relationship until you've and three is a
small number really on the internet
might be like 20 things like you might
have to tell somebody 20 interesting
things before they're like this guy is
interesting I can't wait to get his next
one and you just have to build that up
like you have to build you have to
consistently be telling somebody
something interesting um multiple times
for you to earn that that you know
Channel between them where they're now
going to be receiving your content or
they'll be willing to vouch for you and
spread you to another person not just on
the merits of the one thing but because
you are interesting and you consistently
share interesting things and then when
groups of people think you're
interesting it's even more powerful
right because then another person comes
in and just says oh everybody thinks
this guy's interesting cool I'll follow
right like which is why the more Twitter
followers you get the more you're going
to get right uh and it's actually not a
bug people get mad about that like the
rich get richer um it's not a bad thing
it's actually a useful mental shortcut
the people who have earned to follow
are probably likely worth following with
some exceptions but it is a useful hack
versus I have to individually vet every
account to figure out who I want to
follow that's the slow way like I'm
going to follow the people that other
people follow that is it sounds just
like oh you're just being a it's part of
the herd mentality or group think or
whatever but there's a reason it exists
there's like a evolutionary advantage to
doing it too which saves you a lot of
time of having to individually vet every
person so I would say to that person who
wants that distribution it's cool that's
one interesting thing
let's do 20 and you know start with your
friends start with your friends and
family start with some group chats start
with some you know maybe you have to
push the wheel a little bit you know
send it to some people who might find
that interesting that you know of with a
personalized message of why you think
they might find that interesting yeah
you're going to have to do some of that
hustle at the beginning to get to get
the word out but you should also not
like have some expectations that just
because you said one interesting thing
it it deserves to be you know spread
everywhere this is not really how it
works right on Twitter itself you have
built huge audience without writing that
many things and you've had a few things
that just absolutely cranked what do you
think that you understand about that
platform and communicating there that
other people are
missing
well I'll say this I
think it what I did worked on Twitter so
basically I I remember I was at 20,000
followers which is a lot in general but
I was like I want to get to 100 now I'm
at 4 400 so like oh I way overshot that
goal um 400,000 followers but it most i'
I say the generic best practice is be
consistent and uh Define what your Niche
is and then talk about stuff in that
Niche I don't really do that so I would
say I defy that but I don't think that's
what helped I think I almost won in
spite of doing that I think if I had
been more consistent and I had defined
my Niche I would be at a million
followers instead of 400,000 so let me
put that out there even though I didn't
follow the best practices I don't think
the right takeaway
is those are the wrong I think the right
takeaway is it would have been even
bigger had I followed those the one
thing I did get right was I knew when
everybody's attention was on a certain
subject I had an interesting take it's
not my writing so much as it is the
thinking like I'm sure I haven't
listened to all your interviews but I am
sure one of the most common themes is
that great writing is just great
thinking clear writing is just clear
thinking writing helps you think better
and think better thinking helps you
write better there are so so tightly
intertwined that the unhelpful but true
advice is I think I had an interesting
thought to say and I said it at the
right time when people were paying
attention to that subject and then
thirdly I wrote it in an interesting way
that helped the spread of it I wrote
some threat about the metaverse that
went super viral and I don't think it's
because of how I wrote it I think it's
because the thought in it was genuinely
a good thought uh like I remember at the
time Facebook had just rebranded to meta
and Zuck went on on l x Freedman podcast
I was like yeah I read this really
interesting thing on Twitter blah BL
blah it's like he wasn't saying it
because my Pros was great or my grammar
was great or my hook was he read it
because he thought the core idea
underlying idea was unique and
interesting um and I think that's more
what to strive for is like you're
building up these two skill sets having
unique and interesting things to say
being good at packaging ideas two
distinct skill sets you can't do only
one and not the other or it'll reveal
itself to be pretty sh if you just have
interesting things to say and crappy
packaging you'll get very far if you
have great packaging but mundane things
to say people get very fatigued of it it
doesn't really work one of the ways that
I like to judge a writer is like if I
like as a measure when I read their
stuff is like how good is this person at
building a connection with their readers
so some writers like let's take chat GPT
chat GPT is like a zero right can be
super informative right it's you learn a
lot but you're not actually building any
sort of emotional connection same thing
with Wikipedia right and then there's
other people like you I think this is
something that you're very intentional
about and I think that
for the average word that you have there
is like a real connection that is built
I think that you're really focused on
that because of your goals as a Creator
and how do you go about doing that
writing so that it's not going to be
just this one and done but so there's
actually going to be like a glue of like
Sean like I like this guy want to
consume his stuff and actually I want to
consum stuff every single day when you
say connection do what do you mean by
that you mean trust do you mean
likeability what do you mean I think
what I mean is an indispensability from
that Creator so I did the lamest thing
ever once I hired a
consultant who was an expert at personal
branding guy five grand that that feels
like almost feels like you're not even
being serious such framed it as the
lamest thing ever I'm aware how lame it
was and it's not like I was like oh I
want to change my image whatever but I
was like well truth be told if I am a
creator that means I am kind of a
individual brand okay so what and this
person worked with all these people so I
was like all right let's do this it goes
back to the theme of what is something
that is super important that people
something that's valuable that other
people either Overlook or actually would
be embarrassed to do totally and your
boys out embarassed so I'll do it so I
hire this guy and um I sit out and we
talk and I'm like okay I learned a bunch
of things from them one of the things he
taught me with you guys people will
follow you to the ends of the Earth if
you are giving them a
feeling that they can't get anywhere
else more consistently than anybody else
is going to give it to them so what does
that mean he basically was like think of
yourself as a little Shopify store and
you're only skew you're a little you're
a merchant got him your your Merchant
your your only skew is basically
one how somebody feels after they
consume your content so for example um I
used to love Ted Ted back in the TED
Talks I remember TED talks like Ted
Talks used to be the [__] now were so
good people make fun of them or whatever
2014 2012 2014 t with the [__] and um or
even before that I was in college but
they were cool so why do I like a TED
Talk even the sound the music of the the
whoosh out of a talk or the intro s the
sound and the way that it looked it was
like this like training like pav pavian
training of like you're going to hear
one really cool idea in 18 minutes and
you're going to walk away feeling
inspired inspired about the world in
some way inspired to either go do
something inspired that the world is
improving in some way inspired to make a
change whatever and Ted is a merchant of
inspiration and so I thought about that
I was like oh yeah that's right I I list
said comedy podcast why because I get
this feeling that I'm hanging out with
my like my friends my funny friends but
like they're not my friends they're just
comedians that hang out but that's why I
think comedy podcasts are so popular
because they can consistently give
somebody the feeling of camaraderie
[__] with your boys without you ever
having to like actually be funny have
funny friends and go hang out right and
so like you're getting that without the
cost amazing and um so anyways but this
is why like you know we got acquired by
twitch people watch Twitch people watch
other people play video games because
you get the feeling of playing a video
game without having to actually sit down
and buy a system buy the game get good
at the game and play the game you get
the same Rush watching this guy try to
win just by watching it's it's kind of
amazing so once I realize that I was
like oh okay this guy's right you know
what I got to do is pick what feeling I
want people to have and then I got to
deliver all I got to focus on is
delivering that to them more
consistently than anybody else is gonna
give it to them if I do that all my
personal brand dreams will come true um
you know so that was the the big
takeaway that was the lesson I had there
so when you say it seems like you're
intentional about it that's what it
that's the underlying thing that it is
is picking up front what am I trying to
deliver what's the what's that feeling
and then consistently be like all right
how could I do that what's a story I
could tell what's a framework I could
give them what's a nugget I could give
them that would that would do that for
them it seems like I want to talk about
editing and it seems like your thing is
that you're really good at writing for
straps and actually you're not like a
you don't seem like somebody who's like
a eighth revision I'm going to put this
away for you know six years kind of guy
with editing you seem like you're pretty
off the cuff you're sort of like Miss
Excel what does thing want to the
emotion I want to have I would guess
then you sit down you write it then you
go away for a few hours you know maybe
going to walk come back look at it ship
it off right so for you let's bring
together emotion editing how do you edit
for the sort of emotion that you're
talking about there
um okay first thing I learned was from
Sam par he has his principal I think he
came on your show too uh which is the
walkway uh so you f you you do the
shitty draft you dump it and I kind of
knew editing was
important and the mistake I used to make
is I'd edit right away that's terrible
idea don't do that so you first do your
research and your thinking you dump your
you do a quick brain dump and you got to
walk away so you you read it well the
last thing I do I read what I wrote and
then I'm going to like forget about it
so I then will go do stuff so I will go
out I'll go play with my kids I'll go
for a walk and I'm not trying to think
about it at all I know I'll come back to
that later and I know it sucks today I'm
going to go I'm going to edit it later
and make it great I'm certain of that
but I don't consciously think about it
and then I come back to it usually let's
say 4 hours 6 hours 8 hours 24 hours
later and I'll read the thing and
immediately I'll be like oh this bad bad
change this oh why don't I talk about
this instead or I wanted it to have this
takeaway I don't think it has that right
now all right where would I punch that
up like I wouldn't have wrote this if I
didn't think it had the potential to
give you that cuz I was very intenal up
front thinking this will do it it's not
coming through where uh and the analogy
I'll use is like imagine our Rivers
flowing so um there's a useful analogy
because I think a lot of people are like
there's nothing there and I'm going to
make it happen another story you can
tell yourself is it's a river the water
wants to flow my ideas are excellent
people are going to love this they want
to consume this and my ideas are worth
consuming but there's some rocks in the
river that are blocking the flow what
are the Rocks all I got to do if I just
simply remove those the water will flow
nice it was a more empowering thing for
me versus like I got to make this good
it's bad I got to create good it's like
no I kind of assume if I got to the
point of writing something it's got to
be like there's something good in it I
just got to remove the suck out of it
right uh I think Pixar uses that that
analogy too they say uh all movies we
make start with start with suck and our
only job is to just remove the suck with
every draft so they do another revision
say what sucks about it now well it
sucks that the main character is not
that likable because blah blah blah so
then they remove that suck and they come
back again that's kind of the same
mindset so I'll just look at it after
after I come back and I'll say is this
doing what I wanted do I think this is
dope does this do what I want it to do
and if not what are the Rocks I can
remove what's the suck I can remove from
this this part's boring this intro is
doesn't really hint what's GNA what's to
come this ending is just kind of like so
yeah that's it that's the idea I don't
have a good ending okay so then I'll
just find that area and I'll just try to
fix that cool how about with humor what
have you learned about writing with
humor are you formulaic about that have
you studied
it that's where I'm looking now like I'm
starting to to pay attention um what
I've learned so far I'll tell you what
I've learned so far as like a white belt
in the humor game is just uh you know
you don't want it to be humor is the
sauce it's not the entree so some people
are writing something to be funny like
it's this is meant to make you laugh
usually that's not me usually it's I'm
trying to get a point across but I'm
going to make you laugh along the way
which will make this more enjoyable for
you to consume so it's the sauce on the
on the meal but it's not the meat it's
not the protein of the of the of the
thing which is good depressurizes it
it's like oh do apply a little bit here
um that's the first part second part is
all humor is just surprise so um
every joke is a setup and a punch line
but the punch line if you see the punch
line coming it's not very funny so
humorous surprise means I have to set it
up in a way where you don't anticipate
this is what I'm going to say and the
contrast of what you thought I was going
to say and what I actually said is what
makes you laugh so you just kind of have
to look for those moments where there's
a bit of an expect you set up an
expectation and then you subvert the
expectation Jerry Seinfeld article in
the New York Times here's how he starts
it knew this was going to come in come
in clutch and it just came in handy he
goes when I got my first apartment in
Manhattan in the hot summer of 1976
there was no pooper scooper law and the
streets were covered in dog crap I
signed the rental agreement stepped
outside and my car had been towed
despite this I still thought this is the
greatest place I've ever been in my life
you know exactly sets it up pooper
scooper funny work and what's going on
there and I think that maybe we can go
into funny words cuz it is interesting
how certain words have a much higher
propensity to be funny than other ones
right if he had said there was no law
around cleaning up your dogs extren that
that now is very pooper scooper is like
ji old funny right exactly and then he
goes and goes sort of takes her to this
other time period you're thinking about
poop but then he goes my car had been
towed and you're like oh my goodness
this sounds terrible and then you said
surprise which is why I thought about
that he goes despite this I still
thought this is the greatest place I've
ever been in my life and this is in like
this Ode to New York City Theo Von is
super um that's exactly who I was
thinking about he's super popular right
now and he's been great I've followed
him since like the real world days
basically Road Rules days and so he's if
you just listen to him talk like his
brain just does something different he's
his brain is like almost wired different
that was my initial story but I was like
I bet you could practice Theo Ving a
little bit as because like what Theo
does if you've never seen him this not
going to make any sense but if you've
seen him this will make all the sense of
the world which is that the Yon will
basically improvise he has no idea what
he's going to say but he improvises he
uses random language or he'll make up a
story that makes that is totally not
true but it's kind of believable and he
keeps us you know a dead pen face when
he's doing it um you can kind of
practice that and so yeah I think you
know practicing is is obviously the best
way to do it well that's a big one let's
follow this madeup language coming up
with words things that other people
hadn't thought of
and how do you go about doing that like
it's a fun little thing to play around
with one of the things that I did is I
like the thinking through the ju toos so
I wrote a piece about how I fell in love
with the Bible and I was like it needs
some little bit of humor in it because
it's you know it's the Bible right it's
it's it's this it activates a part of
your brain where you're like okay this
is
your exactly right Bible should actually
just say that should be the whole
thing exactly so it activates that I was
like I need that's funny so I was like
okay what is the emotional state that
somebody's in and I was like working on
it I was like serious you know you think
of almost like this fancy library and
then I'm like I would do my Bible
studies at a schotsky parking lot in a
strip ball in the Hill Country and now
you just get this jux position I'm not
sure it was like that funny but I think
that it adds so much life to the piece
and I always try to think of like if I'm
trying to be funny or create suspense
what is the emotional state that the
reader in for most of this piece and
then let me just like what you're saying
like bring a little bit of Tabasco sauce
of the opposite yes yes that's exactly
right and I I think you know an exercise
you can do is um so like a theovon
exercise is basically he takes a thing
so let's say it's uh the Bible so it's
the Bible but what a theovon humor like
kind of Lane he does is he'll he'll call
the Bible something else that's kind of
funny like he'll be like uh you know
he'd be like man that Jesus's binder and
he'll be like it's it's the Bible but
now he call it's Jesus mind then he'll
do another one and he'll be like he's
like that old you know like the old
Himalayan diary and it's like what what
are you saying like he just keeps coming
up with different ways to say the Bible
or he'll just be like you know that that
big brown Behavior book and like he'll
just keep going and like I've never done
this before but like that you could try
that so you could just take anything and
be like I'm going to come with six like
I'm just going to keep going and it's so
hard to do like just now when I was
doing it I don't know I was like why the
hell are you trying to do this live on a
podcast but that's how you get better
right so you know doing that is it
trains your brain in a very different
way of thinking than we are used to and
that pays off because
again common traits uncommonly together
is very very valuable you don't need to
be the funniest nor do you need to be
the smartest if you're pretty smart and
you're kind of funny you're like the
best you know so that's that's my whole
strategy was basically to do that was
like I know I'm not funny enough to be a
comedian but I'm funnier than the
average smart guy and I'm smarter than
the average guy so it's like pretty
smart kind of funny that's a good combo
well it's funny because uh I went to you
know I was at church last weekend and I
was with a friend and basically we after
the service she was like man you know
that was a that was a really good sermon
and I was like well what do you like
about about the pastor and she was like
H you know he does a really good job of
talking about very serious sort of like
weighty things but then layering in tons
of humor right so like he was talking
about he was talking about you know you
could have said good people go to the
light and they're focused on moral
values and integrity and bad people move
to the darkness and they run away from
you know righteousness and stuff and
you're like okay that's not right and he
goes at any moment you can either be a
cockroach or a moth right and I grew up
in South Carolina and you know you go
into the pantry sometimes and there's
some cockroaches on the ground and like
you want to step on those things but
those things fly and they go all over
the place and like they'll start eating
your Ritz crackers I swear those
cockroaches are so big they can
practically pick up the babies and
they'll take them to cockroach land or
wherever right and cockroaches they run
away from the light right and then you
have your moths and the moths they go to
the light and then he like weaves these
cockro and the moths throughout the
entire sermon so you're getting this
like chuckle but then through the
chuckle it's like creating this Avenue
for like extreme depth and somehow it's
in the juxtoposition of those two things
that the surmon ends up really hitting
and the humor like lowers your defenses
on like needing to be a super you know
perfect person and all that and it's
like okay we can have some fun here but
then the fun actually allows us to then
get to the depth and that's framing
right he framed it differently same
principle framed differently all more
accessible uh more fun more more
entertaining more memorable and
memorability is is massively underrated
uh you know what's the point of having
the good ideas if nobody remembers them
right like you know part of your job a
responsibility if you actually have
something worth worth remembering is to
take the time and effort to package it
in a way that is going to be catchy and
memorable um my buddy Trevor who was my
roommate in college he um he made his
whole career doing one thing he
basically reads what white papers which
are like scientific journals they're the
most like boring like read the abstract
read the whole study whatever people
it's crazy the scientist spend their
whole life working on this day and then
they package it in the dullest format
possible again with pride because that's
like a you that's high status High
status for them it's like it's so boring
that only another person who's dedicated
their life to this would possibly read
this which means that none of the
insights get taken to the real world
until you know somebody comes and builds
that bridge so he built that bridge he's
he would go learn something he'd read
this and he'd go talk to the scientists
like some you know somebody's been doing
this for 50 years and you know the
number of people who follow them and
listen to them is like you know 35 and
then my buddy started writing a Blog and
newsletter that eventually YouTube and
he built like a 100,000 person email
list about a really like dry subject
which is like uh you know uh growth
mindset uh which is like how it applies
into classrooms and stuff like that and
so he the way he did it was the same
type of frame he's like imagine two
tigers one tiger grew up in the
zoo um and you know a tiger that grows
up in the zoo you know and he does it
he'll teach this to like third graders
or he'll teach it to the New York
Yankees uh you know CEOs of companies or
you know kids basically he does the same
speech to both of them because it's so
easy to easy to understand so memorable
he's like T tiger that grows up in the
in the zoo has their life been easy or
hard pretty easy right do they fight for
their food or is it given to them it's
given to them okay cool uh jungle tiger
jungle Tiger's life hard right lots of
adversity they have to fight for their
own food they know how to survive blah
blah blah if you take a um Jungle tiger
and you put it in the zoo what happens
they like they'll get bored it's like if
you take a zoo tiger you put it in the
jungle what happens like it's dead like
it doesn't know how to survive and he's
basically like you want to be a jungle
tiger right like and how do you do that
well you have to get out of your comfort
zone the zoo where everything is easy
and handed to you and so when you reach
those moments where you're out of your
comfort zone say to yourself like this
is my jungle tiger I got to Jungle tiger
this right now because I have to go I
have to put myself out of my comfort
zone to do this he gave them a language
to remember a whole set of principles
that were all previously packaged in
very boring scientific terms you know
one of the things that I'm noticing from
from you like I always think okay I'm
doing these interviews like how is my
writing process going to change and one
of the biggest things I picked up is I
don't need to learn from writers at all
what I'm going to do is I'm going to go
study Comedians and I'm going to be more
deliberate about finding communicators
who I really like and then trying to say
what are they doing and then bring that
into my writing and then also I think
that you really see a fluidity between
mediums that talking writing humor
storytelling these things can all sort
of play together and they're sort of
like paint colors where yeah you can
have you know you have the white paint
the black paint the blue paint the green
paint but then you can also have like a
you begin to mix them together and then
you can get all these different colors
and that maybe we shouldn't be thinking
about writing as like all these separate
Lanes actually for a lot of the
different skills that you want to learn
to make yourself a better writer don't
even study writers the best people for
that might be in a totally far off field
yeah yeah you you nailed it uh good job
you synthesized it very very well I I do
think it's a good strategy um to
basically pick and choose from adjacent
Fields because you're going to do
something different than other than you
will only looking in your own lane it
becomes very uh it's why everything
becomes the same because we all look at
the same things we all study the same
things and so like you know I was
hanging out with Mr Beast and he said
the same thing I was like what YouTube
channels do you like he's like I don't
really watch YouTube that much anymore
like you're the number one YouTuber in
the world you like live and breathe
YouTube he's like yeah my channel but
then I was like so where do you learn
from he's like well right now we think
that one thing we're weak at is
character development so we study shows
TV shows and movies that are good at
character development or uh whatever and
then he's like trying to steal from
other areas than he's like everybody
else if you're just on YouTube looking
at other YouTube you'll just become lost
in a just sea of sameness and um I I
think that's a a useful tip for people
to to take on I want to end here if you
know you built a newsletter called milk
Road and you had to train another writer
to write your voice and you believe that
learning to write is actually teachable
so when you're teaching other people to
write what were some of the things that
you focused
on uh yeah so we Tau uh the teaching was
important because I didn't want that we
had to send the email out every morning
at like 6: a.m. I was like I'm not doing
that like I'm not good with consistency
anyways I don't wake up that early uh I
know that no matter how fun this is that
I will hate doing by like day 30 so from
day one I was like I'm not going to
write this but it's going to be in my
voice and style how do you do that hired
a guy who's never written before and I
sat him down and I was like um first my
business partner I was like you write
this and I was the editor I was I was
his editor for 30 days and I said cool
now you're the editor now you got to
hire a writer we hired a guy i' never
written before um in any professional
capacity or even blogged I don't I don't
think he had a Blog either uh but I told
him and basically what we did was we
took off one thing that helped as the
newsletter was a consistent format so it
wasn't like 10 different formats it was
one format and I broke down why we write
it the way we write it line by line our
opening line at milk Road was always
like good morning this is the milk Road
the you know and we would say what we do
and then we would say in a funny and
then we would would add a we' tag it
with a joke so we would say we are the
number one source for figure out what
happened in crypto yesterday um think of
us like um think of us like a toaster
strudel a fresh tasty sweet for you in
uh treat for you in the mornings and
then parentheses we tag the joke again
and we would just be like what the f
happened to toast of strugles anyways
kids these days they're missing out
right and it's like we would tag we we'
always tag the joke and we'd be like we
are uh GM we're the we're the milk road
we are
we give you exactly everything you need
to know about crypto in the morning and
nothing nothing that you don't need to
know um and then we would say we would
tag him i' be like um I would say
something like
we're uh reading this newsletter is is
the second best feeling in the world the
first best of course is when you're in a
car you roll down the window and you
start doing that cool dolphin thing with
your hands right like some relatable
funny thing that's just like put you in
a good mood and we were like can we get
them can we get you to smile and can we
get you to be like I like I love these
guys can we give you a reason to open
this that's not based on the Bitcoin
price was another way of thinking about
it and so we that so I started training
I was like the first line this is what
we do here's why we're doing it and
here's 10 examples of doing it good and
then he was like cool got it I can I can
pattern match to that the other thing
that we did was he was um he was doing
the school thing where he's like he
thought he had to be a different guy
like oh maybe I need to be a really
sophisticated do sophisticated analysis
or I need to do kind of like people
think think when they write they need to
do something outside of themselves yeah
the whole point of writing is to take
you and just push it out and so don't
try to create this fake thing that you
think other people might want just take
you and push it out and so for example
he would talk about subjects and the
writing was fine but the subject was
boring so I was like dude why'd you pick
this he's like I don't know I felt like
you know it was in the news people
needed to know about I was like do you
care about this no not really and I was
like would you have ever like texted me
or slack slack message me or send me a
voice note being like dude did you hear
about this this thing's awesome or this
is crazy did you hear about this this is
really interesting he's like no I would
never say that I'm like cool why are we
telling why are we telling 200,000
people about this if you wouldn't tell
me and so what I made him do I was like
every morning I want you to send a voice
note send a voice M and just tell me the
news before you write anything just be
like oh yeah everybody on Twitter's
freaking out because they're worried
about this uh thing that happened or um
price is up today because of because
there's rumors about this right now and
what that means is that if that happened
then this would happen so he would just
say it to me and it was it was such a
good filter because he could stop
himself if he was going to tell me
something that was boring he would catch
himself like I would never say this to
somebody it's boring to me and it'll be
boring to you so it filtered out the
subject beautifully so like those are
the two big things was showing him what
we do in like giving him a sample and
then saying here's what good looks like
here's 10 more examples of good um and
then secondly installing that one step
of like don't do that imp Foster thing
where you start talking about [__] that
you're not even that interested in cuz
guess what nobody else is interested in
it like and the filter for that was send
me a voice mem if it's not interesting
in the voice memory it's definitely not
going to be interesting in long text why
do you think that dolphin thing is so
funny is hilarious relatable and like
you know it's it's not even as funny
it's just like funny that we put again
it's unexpected like why are you writing
this um you know everybody says we're
the best we said we're the second best
thing in the world so immediately like
what's first best first best and then I
can't say a serious thing I have to say
an unserious thing so I'm like the first
best thing is this feeling because we
all know this feeling is great like you
know that feeling it's an amazing
feeling and so um we just knew like okay
things like that are surprising likable
funny you can do them in one line so
it's not like you have to like set up a
long story or joke it was very useful
very efficient as a like mechanism there
sweet that was good fun thanks man yeah
absolutely thanks for having me
[Music]
a